<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>63</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv města Berouna</titleproper>
            <subtitle>The Archives of the Town of Beroun / NAD 63</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Beroun</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>U Archivu 1633, Beroun 2, PSČ 266 01</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 311 622 645</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/beroun/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-beroun@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1404/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>63</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv města Berouna</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Poor</physfacet>
                <extent>139,59 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Beroun</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1404/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Beroun Municipality; Additional creators: Magistrat of the Town of Beroun; Municipal Office of Beroun; National Committee of Beroun</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>The Archives of the Town of Beroun / NAD 63</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>Despite considerable losses, especially in the pre-municipal registry, the fonds documents the development of the town from the 15th century to the present. The fonds was organized and inventoried in 1960-1965. The books were divided into three time periods with divides in 1786 (establishment of the regulated municipality office), 1850, and 1945. The file material is arranged according to the original registry systems and is partially accessible using the original registry finding aids. Only the oldest part until 1786 has an artificial order, as it is a fragment. The final inventory was made in 1980. The additions were processed in 1999.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>Beroun as a town is mentioned in a document from 1265. The town was administered by the town office with 12 councilors and the mayor. The regulated municipality office was established in 1786 and functioned until 1849. After 1848, a Jewish minority engaged in trade began to form there. The Jews had their own prayer house and cemetery.From 1850, the elected town council headed the mayor administered the town affairs. Since 1855, the town was the seat of the district governor's office, in 1868 being transferred to Hořovice. In 1936, the district office was restored there. During the German occupation, a government commissioner was appointed the mayor. In 1945, a revolutionary national committee was established there.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents of the Beroun Municipal Office, deeds, official books, file material, and accounting material. Jews are explicitly mentioned in the following documents: inv. no. 3792 Jewish Oath (1723); Inv. no. 1680 Jews, marriage and residence permits (1836-1849); Inv. no. 2264 Jews - list of Jewish houses, Aryanization of Jewish property (1940-1948); Inv. no. 2264 File of Beroun Jews (in box no. 681) 1942; Inv. no. 2279 Jewish School (1948); Inv. no. 3657 Domicile protocol for the born persons of the Jewish faith (1842-1848); inv. no. 3853 Jews, marriage and residence permits in the town (1836-1849); The town also administered the Prince Rudolf Foundation for the Poor Widow of the Catholic and Jewish Religions from Seligman Ellbogen and the Seligman Ellbogen Foundation for the Ten Poor. Jews can also be mentioned in: the Lists of Beroun house owners according to house numbers (1846); trade agenda of the town and inv. no. 2272 Name changes, search for missing persons, declarations of death, list of persons executed and tortured in concentration camps (Czechs, Jews) (1945-1949).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds contains documents, official books, file material, accounting material, and other material.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Kolektiv okr. archivu: Archiv města Beroun 1404-1945 (1952). Inventář, 2013, 277 s., ev. č. 33.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>GARKISCH M.: Archiv města Berouna – Dodatky 1509-1945 (1950). Inventář, 2010, 51 s., ev. č. 821.</p></otherfindaid>
        <otherfindaid><p>http://soapraha.bach.cz/soapraha/NavigBean.action?entity=%28%5En%29%28%28%28localArchiv%2C%5En%2Chot_%29%28unidata%29%29%28177596%29%29; http://soapraha.bach.cz/soapraha/NavigBean.action?entity=%28%5En%29%28%28%28localArchiv%2C%5En%2Chot_%29%28unidata%29%29%28220710%29%29</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>Aryanisation</subject><subject>Jewish School</subject><subject>Jewish foundations</subject><subject>List of Jews</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>2</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Beroun</titleproper>
            <subtitle>The District Office of Beroun / NAD 2</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Beroun</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>U Archivu 1633, Beroun 2, PSČ 266 01</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 311 622 645</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/beroun/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-beroun@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1850/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>2</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Beroun</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Good</physfacet>
                <extent>78 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Beroun</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1850/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Governor's Office Beroun; District Office of Beroun; District National Committee Beroun</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>The District Office of Beroun / NAD 2</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>Only a small fraction of documents from the first period of the activity of the District Office in Beroun have survived, they being probably completely randomly selected files. Presidium files from this period (1855-1868) were saved together with the presidium registry. From the second period of the activity of the District Office in Beroun in the years 1936- 945, the file material has been preserved in its entirety. In 1958, the fonds was taken over by the district archives. In 1960, the fonds was subject to an internal appraisal procedure. It was organized and an inventory was made. The amendments were incorporated later.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The Beroun District Office was established in 1855, when the political administration was merged with the district court, the so-called mixed district office. In 1868, the mixed district offices were abolished and one large district was established - the Hořovice district, which included areas in the previous years administered by the district offices in Beroun, Hořovice and Zbiroh. The Beroun region was part of the Hořovice district until 1936, when an independent political district of Beroun was established. In 1960, the District National Committee was established in Beroun.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents from the activities of the district office: registry finding aids, files, and accounting material. Mentions of Jews can be found in Group VII, Education, Religious, matrimonial, register and fund matters 1936-1948: inv. no. 61 Jewish religious communities, and group X, Agricultural, hunting, forestry and water management matters inv. no. 468 X/1 Applications for registration of Jewish Property - 67. The presidium files of the District Office in Beroun are the most valuable part of the fonds. The registry contains the subject group Jews. Specifically, they are: documents concerning anti-Jewish riots in the district in 1866: - inv. no. 18 - A report about anti-Jewish riots; inv. no. 19 Selling sticks to Jews to defend themselves "when being attacked"; inv. no. 20 Anti-Jewish songs; inv. no. 21/inv. no. 22 /inv. no. 25/inv. no. 27/inv. no. 30/inv. no. 35/inv. no. 36/ inv. no. 37/inv. no. 38 - Anti-Jewish riots; inv. no. 39 Position of rabbi - Samuel Pražák of Rakovník (1867); inv. no. 345 Migration of Jews from Germany (1936); inv. no. 250 Collection of files concerning Jews (marking of shops, list of Jewish enterprises, contact of Jews and Aryans, etc.) 1941; inv. no. 303 Anti-Jewish slogans on houses (1939); inv. no. 1672 Seizure of radios from Jews (1939).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided as follows: I. Official books; II. File material - registry finding aids and files; III. Accounting material; IV. Other material. The file material is divided into four handling periods.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Holeček J.: Okresní úřad Beroun 1850-1950. Inventář, 1963, 67 s., ev. č. 21.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Drtinová S. – Holeček J.: Okresní úřad Beroun – Presidiální spisy 1855-1938. Katalog, 1972, 49 s., ev. č. 22.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Drtinová S. – Holeček J.: Okresní úřad Beroun – Presidiální spisy 1939-1945. Katalog, 1972, 49 s., ev. č. 23.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Garkisch M.: Okresní úřad  Beroun – Dodatky 1850-1945 (1966). Dočasní invetář, 1998, 19 s., ev. č. 835.</p></otherfindaid>
        <otherfindaid><p>http://soapraha.bach.cz/soapraha/NavigBean.action?entity=%28%5En%29%28%28%28localArchiv%2C%5En%2Chot_%29%28unidata%29%29%28165591%29%29</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>Antisemitism</subject><subject>Anti-Jewish riots</subject><subject>Jewish Religious Society</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>34</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Hořovice </titleproper>
            <subtitle>District Office of Hořovice / NAD 34</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Beroun</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>U Archivu 1633, Beroun 2, PSČ 266 01</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 311 622 645</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/beroun/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-beroun@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1850/1942</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>34</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Hořovice </unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Poor</physfacet>
                <extent>128,4 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Beroun</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1850/1942</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Governor's Office Hořovice; District Office of Hořovice</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>District Office of Hořovice / NAD 34</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The file material of the first four handling periods (1850-1909) was handed over to the archives of the Ministry of the Interior in Prague in 1932 after a previous accidental appraisal, and in 1960 the State Archives in Prague handed it over to the District Archives in Beroun. The other material was stored for a long time together with the registry of the Hořovice district council in the registry office of the district office and the District National Committee in Hořovice. In 1960, the entire fonds was concentrated in Beroun and organized, an inventory and a catalog of presidium files being made, too.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The district governor's office in Hořovice began its activities in 1850. From 1855, the political administration was connected with the district court (the so-called Mixed District Office). In 1868, the district governor's offices were restored and the Hořovice district was established, including the former district offices in Beroun, Hořovice and Zbiroh. In 1918, the new state took over the political division of the country virtually unchanged, and only the designation of the district governor's office was changed to the political district administration. From 1928, the designation of the district office was re-introduced, but as early as 1942, the district office was abolished and the municipalities it previously administered were affiliated to the Beroun district. On June 1, 1945, the District National Committee was established in Hořovice.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents arising from the activities of the district administration in Hořovice. It contains official books, files including census records, and accounting material. In general, references to the Jewish population can be found in Group VII Education and enlightenment, Religion, marital registry and fund matters. Registration books: trade agenda and lists of issued domicile certificates (1856-1924); Register of changes of religion 1906-1940. The fonds also includes census records from 1880, 1890, 1900 and 1910. Jews are explicitly mentioned in the following documents: Inv. no. 848 Jewish religious communities, Inv. no. 881 Jewish land records, Inv. no. 124 Record of heads of Jewish registries, Inv. no. 752 Matters of Roman Catholic, Jewish and Czechoslovak Churches 1921-1930; Inv. no. 847 Jewish religious communities 1940-1942. Presidium files contain rich material on Jewish history: Year 1866: Inv. no. 22/25/26 - Anti-Jewish storms; Inv. no. 67/1874, Inv. no. 112/1874 Leopold Weinstein - honors; Inv. no. 350/1875 Trader Hirsch - sale on credit; Year 1877 Inv. no. 250/269/216 Filling teacher posts; Inv. no. 255/1879 Fischer Reichmann Factory in Hořovice; Inv. no. 115/1883 Physicians Vilém Rissel and Leopold Weinstein; Inv. No. 191/1883 Nathan Schwarzkopf - district physician; Inv. no. 172/1886, Inv. no. 186/1886 and Inv. no. 172/1886 Jewish community in Liteň - construction of the synagogue; Inv. no. 56/1888 Isidor Stein of Pliskov; Inv. no. 224/1889 Sugar factory chemist Antonín Schillinger; Year 1890: Inv. no. 150 and 154 Anti-Jewish threats to Leopold Neumann of Beroun by workers, Inv. no. 174/1890 Anti-Jewish leaflets; Inv.no. 177/1890 Refusal to protect the Jewish community in Hořovice; Inv. no. 250/1892 Seligman Elbogen - imperial decoration; Inv. no. 47/1887 Jew Freund of Olešná, attempted assassination; Inv. no. 141/1893 Anti-Jewish poster; Inv. no. 150/1893 Dr. Emil Wiesenberger - Beroun, Inv. no. 327/1893 Anti-Jewish articles; Inv. no. 403/1893 Death of a maid serving to Jew Löwi in Beroun; Inv. no. 427/1893, Inv. no. 3/1898, Inv. no. 408/1908 Anti-Jewish manifestation in Beroun; Inv. no. 436/1893 Anti-Jewish riots, list of all Jews living in Beroun; Inv. no. 116/1894 The Czech-Jewish National Unity in Prague being dissolved, the local branch of the association in Hořovice is to cease its activities; Inv. no. 446/1899 Anti-Jewish riots in connection with the trial of Jew Hilsner; Inv. no. 92/1904 Thanks to the Jewish religious community in Hořovice; Inv. no. 235/1896 Overview of the religious affiliation of the population in the Zbiroh judicial district; Inv. no. 25/1866 and Inv. no. 26/1866, Inv. no. 364/1919 - Anti-Jewish riots and damage to property; Inv. no. 882/1939 Restrictions on contact between Jews and non-Jews; Inv. No. 1028/1939 List of holiday cottages belonging to Jews; Inv. No. 882/1939 Contact of Jews and non-Jews; Inv. no. 1028/1939 List of holiday cottages belonging to Jews; Inv. no. 1149/1939 Marking Jewish enterprises; Inv. no. 52/1940 Layoffs in Lowit and Tausig firm; Inv. no. 235/1940 Closing Jewish textile shops; Inv. no. 840/1940 Report on the attitude of Czechs to Germans and Jews; Inv. no. 931/1940 and 1339/1940 Restrictions on Jews; Inv. no. 1274 Jewish inn owners; Inv. no. 80/1941 Arresting Anna Poláková, Jew; Inv. no. 113/1941 Restrictions on Jewish companies; Inv. no. 826/1941 Forming groups of Jews to remove anti-German inscriptions; Inv. no. 1147/1941 Restriction of visits to exhibitions, etc. by Jewish persons; Inv. no. 121/1942 Jewish property.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The structure of the fonds: I. Books, A. administrative books, B. registration books; II. File material, A. registry finding aids, B. files; III. Accounting material</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Drtinová S.– Holeček J. – König J.: Okresní úřad Hořovice 1850-1942 (1956). Inventář, 1963, 99 s., ev. č. 1.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Drtinová S. – Holeček J. – Hrubá M.: Okresní úřad Hořovice – Presidiální spisy 1851-1917. Katalog, 1972, ev. č. 2.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Drtinová S. – HOLEČEK J.: Okresní úřad Hořovice – Presidiální spisy 1918-1938. Katalog, 1972, 124 s., ev. č. 3.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Drtinová S. – HOLEČEK J.: Okresní úřad Hořovice – Presidiální spisy 1939-1942. Katalog, 1972, 29 s., ev. č. 4.</p></otherfindaid>
        <otherfindaid><p>http://soapraha.bach.cz/soapraha/NavigBean.action?entity=%28%5En%29%28%28%28localArchiv%2C%5En%2Chot_%29%28unidata%29%29%28214860%29%29</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>Domicile certificates, Anti-Jewish riots, anti-Jewish restrictions, Jewish property, anti-German inscriptions</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    