<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>6</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv města Kaňk</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Archives of the Town of Kaňk / NAD 6</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Kutná Hora</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Benešova 257/33, Kutná Hora, PSČ 284 80</addressline>
                <addressline>+420 321 024 353, + 420 737 277 820 (mobile phone), +420 321 024 360 (research room)</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/kutnahora/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-kutna.hora@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1487/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>6</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv města Kaňk</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                <genreform>Cartographic material</genreform> 
                <physfacet type="condition">Good</physfacet>
                <extent>17,59 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Kutná Hora</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1487/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="lat">lat</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language><language langcode="cze">cze</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Kaňk Municipality; Municipal Office of Kaňk, Magistrat of the Town of Kaňk 1793-1850</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Archives of the Town of Kaňk / NAD 6</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The fonds was probably always kept at the town hall. In 1960, the Kaňk Town Archives became part of the District Archives in Kutná Hora. In 1982, a group inventory was developed. The fonds was organized and an inventory made in 2012 - 2013.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The first record appeared in a deed from 1369. Municipal affairs were administered by several councilors headed by the mayor, who were appointed by the Kutná Hora town council. The period 1848 - 1850 was a time of transition towards the municipal self-government. In the self-governing period, Kaňk was an independent local municipality until the Nazi occupation. The reorganization of the town administration, especially the establishment of a system of representation based on political parties, took place after the municipal elections in 1919. From 1939, the village was administered by a government commissioner. Kaňk became a part of Kutná Hora in 1950.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds is the basic source for understanding the political, economic, social and cultural development of the town from the 15th century to 1945. It contains deeds, official books, file material, and accounting material. Information on Jews can also be found in the agenda from the pre-municipal office period of the 18th century. In general, church affairs (1850-1944), in particular, are relevant, specifically inv. no. 1195, the period 1850-1944 Church affairs - priests, cooperator, visitations, festivities, choir, fields, registry affairs, Jews. Explicit mentions of Jews can then be found in the following: inv. no. 1070 Salt trade (salt from a Jew from Ovčáry) 1827-1830; inv. no. 1106 Jews (permits of residence in mining towns) 1801-1848; inv. no. 1141 Proclamation of laws and regulations (regulations against Jews) 1850-1944.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds consists of: I. Deeds until 1850, II. Official books (Books until 1850 and Books after 1850), III. File material (Registry finding aids and files), IV. Accounting material, V. Other (maps, plans, seal matrixes).</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>Accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Vaněčková J.: Archiv města Kaňk 1487-1945 (1948). Inventář, 2013, 170 s., ev. č. 220.</p></otherfindaid>
        <otherfindaid><p>http://soapraha.bach.cz/soapraha/NavigBean.action?entity=%28%5En%29%28%28%28localArchiv%2C%5En%2Chot_%29%28unidata%29%29%28311744%29%29</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>trade</subject><subject>mining towns</subject><subject>anti-Jewish regulations</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
