<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>7</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Kutná Hora</titleproper>
            <subtitle>District Office of Kutná Hora / NAD 7</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Kutná Hora</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Benešova 257/33, Kutná Hora, PSČ 284 81</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 321 024 353, +420 737 277 820 (mobile phone), +420 321 024 360 (research room)</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/kutnahora/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-kutna.hora@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1850/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>7</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Kutná Hora</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Good</physfacet>
                <extent>131,48 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Kutná Hora</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1850/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Governor's Office Kutná Hora; District Office of Kutná Hora (1855-1868, 1928-1945); District Political Administration Kutná Hora (1918-1927)</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>District Office of Kutná Hora / NAD 7</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The fonds was transferred to the archives from the District National Committee building, where the documents had been stored. In 1964 - 1965, the material was arranged and an inventory list was made for it, the additions being made in 1972. In 1967 - 1972, catalogs of the presidium files from 1850-1945 were made. The fonds contains administrative and registration books from the years of (1794) 1850-1945 (1957) and presidium files from the years of 1850 -1945. The common registry included in the handling periods has been fully preserved from the period after 1900 (until 1900 only fragments have been preserved). Filing protocols and registry finding aids have been preserved from the entire period of the district office.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The district office was in operation in the years of 1850 - 1945. In 1850, the district governor's office was established in Kutná Hora with jurisdiction over the Kutná Hora and Čáslav judicial districts. From 1855 to 1868, there was the so-called mixed district office (judicial and political administration) there, the administration being carried out in that period only in the judicial district of Kutná Hora. In 1868, the Uhlířské Janovice judicial district was added to it. After 1868, the district governor's office was restored, and the judiciary was separated from the administration. In 1919, the district governor's office was renamed the district political administration. In 1927, the name was again changed to the district office. Its activities ended with the establishment of the District National Committee.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds originated from the activities of the political administrative office of first instance. It contains official books, file material, and accounting material. The fonds contains the census of 1921 from the judicial districts of Kutná Hora and Uhlířské Janovice.Documents on the history of Jews can mainly be found in the following documents: religious, federal and assembly matters, domicile especially in the 5th handling period (1936-1946), Groups III Security and VII Education; religion, marriage, registry and endowment matters, and matters; specifically, inv. no. 1381 VIII/19 Jewish flats; inv. no. 1350 VIII/8 Domicile applications (Jews, Germans) 1941-45; inv. no. 1302 VII/25 Jewish religious events 1936-46; inv. no. 5 5/7 Statutes of the Jewish religious community from 1892; inv. no. III. 21b/P 628 - Investigation of Jews from Chrastá 1940; inv. no. 21b/Š 517 Breaking windows of Jewish homes; inv. no. Group VI 1/168 Jewish enterprises, their property, the number of employees 1939, inv. no. 1/282 Expulsion of Jews from the economy of the Protectorate 1940; inv. no. VII 25 Jewish religious community; inv. no. VII 25a/7 Permission for the journeys of Jews, movement of the Jewish population, lists of Jews, marking of Jews, actions against Czechs showing sympathy to Jews, Jewish half-breeds, use of public transport by Jews, measures to place Jews in closed settlements 1941-44. For the older period, we can find in the presidium files the following: inv. no. 11/1866 Riots and Jews; inv. no. 19/1866 Breaking windows of Jewish homes; inv. no. 24/1866 Anti-Jewish riots; inv.no. 44/1866 Breaking windows, Červené Janovice; inv. no. 31/1854 Anti-Jewish letter; inv. no. 29/1853 Price fixing done by Jews; inv. no. 290/1911 Promotion of military service included in the teaching of Jewish religion; inv. no. 8/1917 Condolence telegram of the Jewish National Association of Kutná Hora; inv. no. 2472/1915 Investigation of persons posing as candidates for the rabbi - false news; inv. no. 40/1915 Jews - refugees from Galicia; Concerning the accusation of ritual murder in the so-called Hilsner Affair, the following items are relevant: inv. no. 226, 359; 1899; then inv. no. 402/1900 and inv. no. 108/1901. From the period before the Second World War and the war period, the following items are relevant: inv. no.970/1936 Migration of Jews, foreign nationals to Czechoslovakia; inv. no. 1444/1936 Suicide attempt by A. Guth, a German Jew; inv. no. 995/1938 Punishment of Prof. Dr. E. Stein; inv. no. 1340/1938 and inv. no. 716/1939 Anti-Jewish leaflets; inv. no. 713/1939 Situation report from February 2, 1939 - anti-Jewish leaflets, confiscation of Jewish property; inv. no. 717/1939 Derogatory inscriptions on a Jewish doctor's office and shops; inv. no. 190/1939 Jews in the civil service; inv. no. 353/1939 and also inv. no. 646/1939 Jewish property, inv. no. 380/1939 Jewish firm Respo Reininger; inv. no. 570/1939 Jewish question; inv. no. 747/1939 List of Polish Jews; inv. no. 833/1939 Seizure of radio sets from Jews; inv. no. 812/1939 Searches of Jewish homes; inv. no. 387/1941 Contact between the Jewish and non-Jewish populations; inv. no. 421/1941 Payments made by Jews; inv. no. 836/1942 Anti-Jewish regulations; from 1940, inv. no. 841, 906, 949; from 1941 inv. no. 671, 718, 965, and 354/1942.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into Books (Administration and Registry), Files (including auxiliary books) and Accounting material. The files are further divided into presidium files and 5 common file handling periods. Earlier handling periods have only been preserved in fragments. The fonds also contains a census of 1921 from the judicial districts of Kutná Hora and Uhlířské Janovice.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Kolektiv: Okresní úřad Kutná Hora 1850-1945 (1951). Inventář, 1972, 119 s., ev. č. 3.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Kapavíková M. – Vlček Z. – Vlčková M.: Okresní úřad Kutná Hora – Katalog presidiálních spisů, Sv. 1., 1. 1. 1850-27. 10. 1918. Katalog, 1973, 340 s., ev. č. 4.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Moravová L. – Vlčková M.: Okresní úřad Kutná Hora – Katalog presidiálních spisů, Sv.2., 28. 10. 1918-14. 3. 1939. Katalog, 1968, 96 s., ev. č. 5.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Moravová L. – Vlčková M.: Okresní úřad Kutná Hora – Katalog presidiálních spisů, Sv.3., 15. 3. 1939-9. 5. 1945. Katalog, 1967, s. 53, ev. č. 6.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Frydová V. – Kapavíková M. – Moravová L. – Vlčková M.: Okresní úřad Kutná Hora – Rejstříky ke katalogům presidiálních spisů, I. - III. Díl, 1850-1945. Register, 1973, 99 s., ev. č. 7.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Moravová L.: Okresní úřad Kutná Hora – Konkréta 1850-1946. Katalog, 1972, 30 s., ev. č. 15.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>Census records</subject><subject>anti-Jewish leaflets</subject><subject>Jewish property</subject><subject>Polish Jews</subject><subject>Anti-Jewish regulations</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    