<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>57</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Kolín I</titleproper>
            <subtitle>District Office of Kolin I / NAD 57</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Kolin</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Zahradní 278, Kolín IV, 280 02</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 321 724 273</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/kolin/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-kolin@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1850/1948</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>57</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Kolín I</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">good</physfacet>
                <extent>263,06 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Kolin</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1850/1948</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Office of Kolín; District Governor's Office Kolín (ger.Bezirkshauptmannschaft Kolin); District Political Administration Kolín (ger. Bezirksverwaltung Kolin); District Office of Kolín (ger. Bezirksbehörde Kolin)</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>District Office of Kolin I / NAD 57</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The first report on the fonds dates to 1930. The files were kept in the district office building. A small part of the files was lent to the former archives of the Czech Lands. In 1960, the district archives in Kolín took over these files back from the State Central Archives in Prague. After the war, the files were moved to an unsuitable room, where they were kept until 1956. Only then were the materials transported to the building of the district national committee in Kolín. Since 1960, the files have been organized.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The districts were established in 1850 as a replacement for the original manor. It was an administrative body. After the establishment of Czechoslovakia, the District Governor's Office in Kolín was referred to as the Kolín District Political Administration. From 1928, it was designated the Kolín District Office.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents concerning the economy, agriculture, business, and industry in the district of Kolín between 1850 and 1948, official books, files and accounting material. An important part of the fonds includes presidium files. There are relevant files on religious matters there from 1850–1936 (Group 5). For the years of 1924–1936, there is a section on the Jewish church (inv. No. 843, call number 5/4). There can also be found lists of the Jewish population from 1942 (inv. No. 1104, call number 7/33/a), statements on the change of residence of Jewish persons (1939–1943), notifications on the implementation of anti-Jewish measures (1939–1942), as well as lists Jewish shops and trades from 1940. Attention should also be paid to files on association and assembly matters from 1913-1936, trade matters (1913–1948), and files on persons' moving, passports, and emigration.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into I. Books (administrative books, registration books), II. File material: A. registry finding aids B. files III. Accounting material.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Bisinger Z.: Okresní úřad Kolín I – Presidiální spisy 1850-1918. Katalog, 1970, 113 s., ev. č. 17.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Bisinger Z.: Okresní úřad Kolín – Presidiální spisy 1918-1939. Katalog, 1970, 0 s., ev. č. 18.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Okresní úřad Kolín – Presidiální spisy 1939-1945. Katalog, 1967, 45 s., ev. č. 19.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Bisinger Z. – Startl J.: Okresní úřad Kolín 1850-1948. Inventář, 1963, 195 s., ev. č. 20.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>religious matters</subject><subject>Jewish Religious Community</subject><subject>lists of the Jews</subject><subject>anti-Jewish measures</subject><subject>Jewish businesses</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
