<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>283</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv města Hradec Králové</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Archives of the City of Hradec Králové / NAD 283</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Hradec Králové</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Škroupova 695/2, 500 02 Hradec Králové</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 495 402 611</addressline>
                <addressline>https://vychodoceskearchivy.cz/home/kontakty/statni-okresni-archiv-hradec-kralove/</addressline>
                <addressline>podatelna.hk@ahapa.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1225/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>283</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv města Hradec Králové</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">good</physfacet>
                <extent>243,85 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Hradec Králové</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1225/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="lat">lat</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language><language langcode="cze">cze</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Archives of the City of Hradec Králové</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Archives of the City of Hradec Králové / NAD 283</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The oldest documents have largely not been preserved, being destroyed in the years 1873-1875. The city privileges were handed over to the district archives in 1954, and in 1960 the first list of documents was made. The inventory of the fonds began shortly before the First World War and was completed with partial breaks in 1980. After the inventory, archival finding aids were created.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The first record dates from 1225. In 1851, Hradec Králové was declared an independent town. During the Nazi occupation, Hradec was transformed into the so-called Great Hradec Králové absorbing the adjacent small towns and suburbs. At the head of the city there was the city committee with the mayor. In 1945, the Revolutionary National Committee was established. Jewish settlement had existed there since the 14th century. The modern religious community was established in 1860, being restored after World War II. The first synagogue was built in the years 1888-1905, the new synagogue then in the years 1904-1905. Its interior was adapted for the State Scientific Library in 1960. In the city there is a cemetery founded in 1877.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds is very large and covers the entire history of the city of Hradec Králové. It contains official books, deeds, file material and accounting material. Relevant information can be assumed in the inventory numbers 2184 and 2598. This is an extract from the register where Jews are mentioned. The numbers 2184 (restitution of Jewish property) and 2598 deal with their property, i.e. these are documents from the period 1939-1949. It is possible to assume mentions of the Jews in inv. No. 381 (book of inheritance statements and divided estates [1841-1848/1878/]), inv. No. 444 (record book [1830-1855]), and inv. No. 458 (book of manorial land [1836-1877]). Books after 1850, inv. No. 2184 (restitution of Jewish property, more precisely the purchase of a villa in Plotiště, the purchase of a sawmill and a villa of Gustav Stein, restitution of Jewish property [1938-1948]); inv. No. 2598 (order on Jews, Jewish property [1939-1948]).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is arranged both in a numerical order and alphabetically: I. documents, a) documents concerning the city as a whole, b) documents concerning the city and its inhabitants II. books, a) books up to 1526, b) books up to 1850, c) books after 1850 (commemorative, official, and registration books) III. file material, a) auxiliary books, b) files IV. accounting material.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Rejmánek L. – Svatoňová S. – Wipler J.– Zimmermann P.: Archiv města Hradec Králové 1225-1945 (1962), I. Díl. Inventář, 1983, 301 s., ev. č. 210.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Rejmánek L. – Svatoňová S. – Wipler J. – Zimmermann P.: Archiv města Hradec Králové 1225-1945(1962). II. Díl. Inventář, 1983, 165 s., ev. č. 211.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Pavlík J.: Archiv města Hradec Králové 1518-1945. Dílčí inventář, 2002, 44 s., ev. č. 1689.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>restitutions</subject><subject>Jewish property</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>567</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv města Chlumec nad Cidlinou</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Archives of the Town of Chlumec nad Cidlinou / NAD 567</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Hradec Králové</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Škroupova 695/2, 500 02 Hradec Králové</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 495 402 611</addressline>
                <addressline>https://vychodoceskearchivy.cz/home/kontakty/statni-okresni-archiv-hradec-kralove/</addressline>
                <addressline>podatelna.hk@ahapa.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1531/1845</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>567</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv města Chlumec nad Cidlinou</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Poor</physfacet>
                <extent>74,87 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Hradec Králové</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1531/1845</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Archives of the Town of Chlumec nad Cidlinou</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Archives of the Town of Chlumec nad Cidlinou / NAD 567</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The fonds was stored in the rooms of the town hall, later in the attic. In 1868, during the inventory of the town property, the town acquired a detailed list of books and privileges with numbers and inventory designations. In 1928, the oldest books and documents were moved to the museum in Chlumec. In 1956, the town archives became a branch of the archives of the Nový Bydžov district. In 1961, the archives were moved to a room in the chateau. The fonds was organized in 1970-73 and an inventory was created for it.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The first record of Chlumec is from 1325. Originally, this municipality belonged to the Šternberk family. During the first half of the 19th century, a district court, a district office and a district council were established in the town. Patrimonial authorities and municipality offices were to cease operations on 1 January 1850. In June 1850, part of the files were moved from the abolished municipality to the district court in Chlumec nad Cidlinou. In the period 1850-55, the judicial district of Chlumec nad Cidlinou fell under the administration of the governor's office in Nový Bydžov. In the period 1855-1868, the district office in Chlumec administered 44 municipalities with approximately 19,000 inhabitants.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds covers the history of the town of Chlumec nad Cidlinou. It is relatively large, but due to poor storage, part of the fonds was damaged. It contains deeds, official books, file material, accounting material, and other documents. The register mentions Jews (foreigners' notices of moving in and out, and files of Václav Abraham, the merchant, and of Václav Sladkus, inv. no. 1109, 1110). The fonds contains processed files of the Jewish merchant Václav Abraham inv. no. 173 (inheritance book 1833-1853/1883). Furthermore, the Jews are mentioned in inv. no. 281-285 (books of the dead 1850-1869, 1869-1902, 1903-1916, 1916-1931, 1931-1950); inv. no. 326-327 (population list 1870); inv. no. 1058-1066 (censuses, 1906, 1910, 1915, 1925, 1930, 1934, 1937, 1938, 1938, 1945); inv. no.1109 (list of persons of Jewish nationality 1941); inv. no. 1110 (Jews - handing over gold 1940); inv. no. 1112 (files of Václav Abraham, the merchant, and Václav Sladkus 1940-1946).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into: I. Deeds, II. Books, A. Books kept in the interest of the town until 1850, B. Books to ensure the rights and property of burghers and serfs until 1850, C. Books after 1850, III. File material, A. Auxiliary books until 1850, B. Auxiliary books after 1850, C. Files before 1790, D. Handled files of the municipality office 1791-1850, E. Period of the municipal office 1850-1945, IV. Accounting material, V. Others, A. Maps and plans, B. Seal matrixes and stamps</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Hartman J.: Archiv města Chlumec nad Cidlinou (1525/1531-1945/1951). Inventář, 1975, 206 s., ev. č. 173.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>Jewish merchant</subject><subject>books of the dead</subject><subject>census records</subject><subject>list of Jewish nationals</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>454</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Židovská náboženská obec Hradec Králové</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Jewish Religious Community in Hradec Králové / NAD 454</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Hradec Králové</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Škroupova 695/2, 500 02 Hradec Králové</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 495 402 611</addressline>
                <addressline>https://vychodoceskearchivy.cz/home/kontakty/statni-okresni-archiv-hradec-kralove/</addressline>
                <addressline>podatelna.hk@ahapa.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1945/1957</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>454</unitid>
            <unittitle>Židovská náboženská obec Hradec Králové</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">good</physfacet>
                <extent>0,12 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Hradec Králové</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1945/1957</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Jewish Religious Community in Hradec Králové</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Jewish Religious Community in Hradec Králové / NAD 454</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>unknown</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>This is the fonds of the Jewish Religious Community in Hradec Králové, but the files mainly relate to Nový Bydžov.Hradec Králové has been an important city since the Middle Ages. The first report on Jewish settlement dates back to the 14th century, when the Jewish Square and a plan are documented in the surviving documents. There was no synagogue or Jewish school at that time. In 1454 the Jews were expelled from the city. In 1651, Hradec had several Jewish inhabitants and their own rabbi (David Tachovský). In 1860, there was already a Jewish community with an elected board there. In 1877, a funeral fraternity was founded. As a result of internal disputes, the election of the board ceased to be elected in 1890. In the period 1890-1894, the municipality was administered by a committee. Afterwards, Bohumír Weiss was elected the mayor, and the election of the mayor lasted until 1933. In 1905, a synagogue was built in the city instead of the then prayer house.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains mostly the correspondence of the rabbi with members of the Jewish community, lawyers and doctors. In addition to the correspondence, there is also archive material from the period of the Second World War, including the restitution issues of Jewish property. There is also the correspondence of the Jewish religious community in Kolín in the fonds. There are also documents about the first Czech Mutual Insurance Company. The fonds also includes Nazi documents as well as archive material concerning the purchase of the synagogue.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is not arranged.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>There are no finding aids.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><corpname>Czech Mutual Insurance Company</corpname></controlaccess>
        <controlaccess><subject>correspondence of the rabbi</subject><subject>Jewish religious community</subject><subject>Jewish property</subject><subject>synagogue</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    