<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>1154</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv města Vizovice</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Vizovice Town Archives / NAD 1154</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Zlín</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Klečůvka-zámek, 763 11 Želechovice nad Dřevnicí</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 577 901 132</addressline>
                <addressline>www.mza.cz/zlin</addressline>
                <addressline>soka_zlin@mza.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1531/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>1154</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv města Vizovice</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Poor</physfacet>
                <extent>10,24 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Zlín</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1531/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Municipal Office of Vizovice; Vizovice Municipality </name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Vizovice Town Archives / NAD 1154</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The town council documents were stored at the town hall. Most of these documents burned in the fire of 1887, only some were saved. They were later bought by the Moravian Provincial Archives in Brno, from where they were transferred to the fonds of the town of Vizovice in 1969. In the 1960s, the documents were organized and in 1968 placed in the Gottwaldov District Archives (now Zlín).</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The town of Vizovice was first mentioned in a document dating back to 1261. In 1570, Vizovice was promoted to a town. Since 1850 it belonged to the district governor's office in Uherský Brod. A district court, a gendarmerie station and a notary's office were established in Vizovice, and from 1855 the so-called mixed district office. In 1868, Vizovice was included in the district governor's office in Holešov, and the court district remained in Vizovice. In 1935, a new political district of Zlín was formed from the judicial districts of Vizovice and Zlín. The first records of Jews in Vizovice are associated with the manorial distillery from the 17th century. Jews engaged in distillery business in Vizovice and its surroundings also in the 19th century; after 1848, their number expanded. The local Jewish association of Zion operated there. In 1902, a synagogue was built. After the establishment of Czechoslovakia, a branch of the Jewish Party was established in Vizovice.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents of the municipal self-government, deeds, official books, file material and accounting material. It contains only details about Jews: the great distillery of Zikmund Jelínek and Sons, the great distillery in Vizovice - purchase contracts, economic affairs, the inn in Zádveřice, construction plans, the appointment of a "faithful hand" during the 1888–1944 protectorate. The documents from the Holocaust period include the following: inspection and confiscation of supplies in the house of Josef Weiss, No. 417, by the Gestapo 1939; administration of Jewish property and list of Jewish houses and flats 1941–1944. Sufficient attention should also be paid to the following material: the register of members of the municipality and the list of inhabitants according to house numbers 1890–1923; building files and plans 1888–1938; minutes of meetings of the municipal committee 1901–1947.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided as follows: I. Deeds, II. Official books, III. File material, IV. Accountant material, V. Other material.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Štroblík V.: Archiv města Vizovice 1531-1945 (1958). Inventář, 1969, 42 s, ev. č. 204.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><corpname>distillery of Zikmund Jelínek and Sons</corpname></controlaccess>
        <controlaccess><subject>Jewish property</subject><subject>Holocaust</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    

