<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>1282</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní soud Hořice</titleproper>
            <subtitle>District Court in Hořice / NAD 1282</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Jičín</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Raisova 533, 506 01 Jičín</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 491 401 051</addressline>
                <addressline>https://vychodoceskearchivy.cz/home/kontakty/statni-okresni-archiv-jicin/</addressline>
                <addressline>podatelna.jc@ahapa.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1850/1960</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>1282</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní soud Hořice</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">good</physfacet>
                <extent>206,05 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Jičín</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1850/1960</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Court in Hořice</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>District Court in Hořice / NAD 1282</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The documents were stored in the registry of the District Court in Hořice. In 1941, the oldest files were transferred to the Archives of the Ministry of the Interior in Prague, from where they were transferred to the State Archives in Kuks in 1950-1958. There the fonds was organized in 1965 and in 1971 it was transferred to the Jičín District Archives, where it was internally appraised and documents up to 1897 were re-inventoried. Part of the registry was transferred to the office of the successor organization, i.e. the District Court in Jičín, from where the material was gradually transferred to the Jičín archives.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The District Court in Hořice was established due to a new organization of the judiciary in 1850. It ruled in civil and legal proceedings, the land register agenda being transferred to it, and in criminal matters its power was limited to less serious acts. In the years 1855-1868, the political administration was merged with the judiciary into the so-called mixed district office. In 1868, the Hořice District Court became independent again, and in 1948 it was renamed the People's Court in Hořice. In 1960, the Hořice District Court ended its existence, and its agenda was taken over by the District Court in Jičín.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents of the court administration of the Hořice judicial district. Of particular interest are the files from the post-war period, namely M - Declaration of death from 1945-1949 and D - estate file, concerning the property of the respective Jewish families. Files M - Richard and Emilie Passer, Olga Schanzerová, Karel Beutler, Bedřich, Josef and Markéta Lamm, the Berger family, Emilie and Alice Munkova, Lavecký family, Hugo Lewith, the Kaufmann family, Olga Singerová, Irma and Bedřich Baumann, Richard and Štěpánka Strauss, Alfred Hirsch, Otto Putzker, Gustav Kantor, Irena Mautnerová. Files D - the above-mentioned families. When searching for a specific inheritance file, it is possible to use the books of auxiliary records - registers D, which are stored in the registry of the Jičín District Court.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds has only been processed for the oldest period 1850-1897. Books and registry finding aids are registered separately, which are sorted according to individual agendas and file call numbers. According to the valid file plans for the given periods, the files are also sorted, while within each file call number the files are arranged chronologically. The land register agenda is kept separately. For the unprocessed part, the books and registry finding aids are registered separately according to the individual agenda and the files are sorted according to the valid file plans, while within each file call number they are arranged chronologically.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Johnová B. – Heligrová M.: Okresní soud Hořice 1851-1897. Inventář, 1972, 25 s., ev. č. 197.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>district court</subject><subject>declaration of death</subject><subject>inheritance file</subject><subject>Jewish property</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
