<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>7</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Sedlčany</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Sedlčany District Office / NAD 7</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive in Příbram</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>E. Beneše 337, 261 01 Příbram VII</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 318 492 411</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/pribram</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-pribram@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1854/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>7</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Sedlčany</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Poor</physfacet>
                <extent>77,46 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive in Příbram</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1854/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Sedlčany District Office; District Governor's Office Sedlčany; District Political Administration Sedlčany</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Sedlčany District Office / NAD 7</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The documents of the district office were taken over by its successor, the District National Committee of Sedlčany. After its abolition, the material was handed over to the State District Archives in Příbram, where it was organized and inventoried in 1960-1964.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The Sedlčany District Office was established in 1855. It had mixed political and judicial powers. In 1868, it was changed into the District Governor's Office. Its authority was limited to political issues. In 1868, the authority of the district governor's office was extended to the judicial districts of Votice and Sedlec, and so it remained until 1945. After the establishment of Czechoslovakia, the office was renamed the District Political Administration (in 1919) and the District Office (in 1928-1945). A drastic intervention in the district took place in the years 1943-1944, when the northern part of the district was occupied as a SS training ground. In 1945, the district office ceased to exist and its competence was taken over by its successor, the District National Committee of Sedlčany.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains official books and files. The following documents are relevant: Conversion to the Roman Catholic Church and change of name Teresia Kohnová 1900; Jewish Religious Society 1904-1927, 1909-1937; Register of Jews: file 1940-1941 (A-K, L-W) with photographs; trade licenses 1940 (containing an inventory of Jewish property); Jewish religious communities 1938-1941; records of conversions 1938; The Record of Infectious Human Diseases 1940; Presidium files: Measures against agitation and political terror against Jewish citizens in connection with the exercise of their right to vote from the part of the opposition political parties of July 29, 1869; Report on the course of the general meeting of the Sedlčany Department of the Czech-Jewish National Unity of 4 October 1896; Resolution of the town council in Prčice sent to Jewish families living in Prčice, in which they demand that Jews should refrain from provocative German conversations on the streets, September 24, 1911; Report of the district governor's office that there are 13 Polish Jews from the occupied and war zones in the district, June 21, 1916; Seizure of cars of Jewish citizens for the Gestapo in Benešov, 1939; Collection of a fee of CZK 10 for a professional inspection of radio receivers during their confiscation from Jews 1939; A copy of the report from the police station on the arrest of František Chyle and Václav Procházka from Prosenická Lhota on suspicion of blackmailing landowner Josef Počepický from Kosova Hora for contacts with Jew Vítězslav Klepetář 1941; Hate articles in the magazine Aryan Struggle on the unacceptable behavior of Jews, 1941; A report of the police station in Sedlčany on anonymous reports of the behavior of Jews in Kosova Hora and Štětkovice from August 24, 1942; Decrees and circulars regulating the Aryan population's contact with the Jewish population</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into official administrative and registration books. The file material is divided into groups of registry finding aids and files. The files are divided into the presidium registry, the general registry, and the files stored outside the registry plan. The general registry is further divided into individual handling periods: 1855-1868, 1868-1904, 1904-1938, 1938-1946.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Polák S.: Okresní úřad Sedlčany 1855-1945. Inventář, 1966, 73 s., ev. č. 6.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Hlinecký O.: Presidiální spisy Okresního úřadu v Sedlčanech 1868-1918. Katalog, 1973, 195 s., ev. č. 24.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Hlinecký O.: Presidiální spisy Okresního úřadu v Sedlčanech 1939-1945. Katalog, 1972, 105 s., ev. č. 21.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><corpname>Czech-Jewish National Unity</corpname></controlaccess>
        <controlaccess><subject>Jewish Religious Society</subject><subject>conversions</subject><subject>register of Jews</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
