<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>196</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv města Poděbrady</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Archives of the Town of Poděbrady / NAD 196</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Nymburk in Lysa nad Labem</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Zámecká 6/13, p. s. 11, Lysá nad Labem, PSČ 289 22</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 325 551 046</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/nymburk/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-nymburk@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1567/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>196</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv města Poděbrady</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Good</physfacet>
                <extent>113, 83 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Nymburk in Lysa nad Labem</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1567/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="lat">lat</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language><language langcode="cze">cze</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Poděbrady Municipality; Controlled Town Council Poděbrady; Municipal Office of Poděbrady; Martin Paroubkovský Institute of the Poor Poděbrady; Komité for the Support of Polish Refugees Poděbrady</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Archives of the Town of Poděbrady / NAD 196</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The town archive was always kept in the town hall. Documents from the oldest period have not been preserved. The older part of the fonds has been preserved only in fragments. The files of the political department of the municipal office from 1826 to 1850 have been almost completely preserved. The fonds was gradually transferred to the central depository of the Nymburk district archives in Lysá nad Labem in the late 1980s. It was definitively organized and inventoried in 1995-2002. The fonds is equipped with an inventory.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The first record of Poděbrady dates back from 1223. Since the 16th century reports of self-government have been preserved. The administrative body was the town council consisting of 12 councilors who elected the mayor. Since 1850, there had been the municipal committee, which elected the municipal board headed by the mayor, and this municipal establishment lasted until 1919. In September 1940, the town council and the council board council were dissolved, and the town administrative commission was established. In January 1942, a German government commissioner was appointed to Poděbrady. After the war, a local national committee was established.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents arising from the administration of the town of Poděbrady: deeds, official books, file material and accounting material. It also includes census sheets, important for the research of Jewish history. The following documents are relevant for the first half of the 19th century: files of the political department of the Poděbrady municipality office, group VIII. Judaism, tolerance patent (1826 -1850). Specific mentions of Jews can be found in the documents of individual groups (Group I. Regulations, circulars by the regional office and reports on them by the municipality office; III. Political investigation files, criminal issues, political settlements, interrogations of parties; IX. Business matters, insurance against fire, matters of trade, food tax, and fairs, XVI. Matters of the Poděbrady estate and other estates, auction decrees and notices.) Information on Jews can also be found in: Inv. no. 609 Jews - permission to build a Jewish synagogue in Poděbrady, census of Jewish inhabitants (1820); inv. no. I/2 lists of Jews (1827-1842); inv. no. I/15 Jewish affairs (1840-41); inv. no. III/16 thefts, orders to reside in the place domicile, escapes - reporting Jew Josef Štejner (1841-47). In general, documents on the history of Jews in the town can be found in the agenda concerning domicile, religion in trade or tax matters. From the second half of the 19th century, there are the following documents there: inv. no. 682 4/13 (J) School affairs - establishment of a Jewish school (1869-95); inv. no.10/3 synagogue and Jewish school, proposal for their demolition (1940-50); call no. 4/9 Cemetery matters - Jewish cemetery - list of buried Jews (1940-50); inv. no. 1139 4/13 Reports on Jews that they gather in busy places (1940-50); inv. no. 1170 call no. 7/2 and 7/6 - administration of Jewish property, Jewish flats for Germans (1938-50); inv. no.1175 7/5 property of Jews before 1838, seizure of Jewish flats, ban on visiting Aryan restaurants, work duties of Jews; inv. no. 1174 7/6 Reports about damage to Jews (1945-50) (alphabetically by individuals); inv. no. 1135 4/9 Jewish cemetery (1940-1950); inv. no. 1240 12/54 Jewish National Association - establishment of an old people's home for Jews in the Luxor Hotel (1940-50); inv. no. 1170 7/2 Josef Wiener - purchase of a synagogue by the town (1948); inv. no. 1170 7/2 administration of apartments, administration of Jewish property (1938-1950).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into: I. Deeds, II. Official books, III. File material: a) registry finding aids b) general agenda files c) domicile right files d) police office files e) census, IV. Accounting material, V. Miscellaneous.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Šmilauerová E.: Archiv města Poděbrady 1567-1945 (1951). Inventář, 2003, 51 s., ev. č. 928.</p></otherfindaid>
        <otherfindaid><p>http://soapraha.bach.cz/soapraha/NavigBean.action?entity=%28%5En%29%28%28%28localArchiv%2C%5En%2Chot_%29%28unidata%29%29%2847236%29%29</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><corpname>Jewish National Association</corpname></controlaccess>
        <controlaccess><subject>Synagogue</subject><subject>Domicile rights</subject><subject>Jewish school</subject><subject>Jewish cemetery</subject><subject>Jewish property</subject><subject>Jewish flats for Germans</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
