<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>195</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Archiv obce Hroubovice</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Archives of Hroubovice / NAD 195</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive Chrudim</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Filištínská 37, Chrudim, 537 01</addressline>
                <addressline> + 420 469 660 408</addressline>
                <addressline>https://vychodoceskearchivy.cz/home/kontakty/statni-okresni-archiv-chrudim/</addressline>
                <addressline>podatelna-cr@ ahapa.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1800/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>195</unitid>
            <unittitle>Archiv obce Hroubovice</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">good</physfacet>
                <extent>0,63 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive Chrudim</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1800/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="cze">cze</language><language langcode="ger">ger</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>Municipal Office of Hroubovice; Municipality of Hroubovice</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>Archives of Hroubovice / NAD 195</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The fonds is stored in the State District Archives in Chrudim. It was organized in 1978 and the first additions were made to the archives in 1956. The fonds was organized in the form of a combined inventory of the Archives of Municipalities of the Chrudim District, Part I B-L. In 2012, it was again included in the unprocessed fonds.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The municipality of Hroubovice belonged to the Košumberk and Chrást estates in the 19th century. There had been an important Jewish community in the municipality since the 18th century. At the beginning of the 19th century, it formed up to 50 percent of the municipality's population. At the end of the 18th century, an independent Jewish religious community was established, and a ghetto was built, in the center of which stood a synagogue and a school - until the 1970s. There were many Jewish businessmen and a few factories in the municipality, e.g. the Werner and Werson shoe factory, the V. Klein chemical factory, and several domestic manufacturers (Lampl, Nettl, Husch). The Mandelík family is important.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains a fragment of municipal documents, file material and official books. Sources for the local Jewish community can be found there. The chronicles of the municipality until the Second World War have been preserved, in which there are data on the inhabitants moved to concentration camps, as well as on the economic prosperity in the 20th century. The life of the community can also be examined in the minutes of the meetings of the council (1902-1921), whose members were representatives of Jewish families. The families can be searched in the municipal register (1902-1948), the register of the inhabitants and foreigners (1900), the list of foreigners (1920-1942), and the criminal record (1874-1924). The fonds also contains a domicile agenda (1888-1941), a list of Galician refugees (1916-1917), criminal records (1897-1945) and files concerning the disputes of two Jewish families - the Lampls and the Huschs (1929-1945).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds contains file material and official books in the range of 4 boxes.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>accessible upon request</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Šáda F.: Archivy obcí chrudimského okresu, díl I. B-L, Chrudim, 1978.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><corpname>Werner and Werson manufacture of footwear</corpname></controlaccess>
        <controlaccess><subject>municipal governmnet</subject><subject>Galician refugees</subject><subject>Holocaust</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    