<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>46</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Praha-venkov</titleproper>
            <subtitle>District Office of Praha-venkov / NAD 46</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive of Prague-West in Prague</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Pražská 728, Dobřichovice, PSČ 252 29</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 257 710 492</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/praha-zapad/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-praha.zapad@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1927/1942</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>46</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Praha-venkov</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Good</physfacet>
                <extent>178,51 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive of Prague-West in Prague</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1927/1942</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="ger">ger</language><language langcode="cze">cze</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Office of Smíchov; District Office of Praha-venkov; District Office of Praha-venkov-jih; District National Committee Praha-jih. </name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>District Office of Praha-venkov / NAD 46</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The office's registry files were kept in the office building. Registries from the former District Political Administration in Smíchov, Karlín and Zbraslav were also transferred there. In the 1920s, part of the office was handed over to the Archives of the Capital City of Prague. The registry of the Smíchov and Karlín District Councils was almost completely destroyed. Part of the documentation was destroyed, and part was taken over in 1960 by the District Archives of Praha-východ, and later the District Archives of Praha-západ. In 1963, the documents of the so-called economic department were added to the fonds. The fonds was organized in 1959-1961. An inventory was made in 1963.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The district political administration for Praha-venkov started its activities in 1927. It originated from the rest of the political districts of Smíchov and Karlín. In 1928, the Praha-venkov political district was divided into 4 judicial districts. (Zbraslav, Praha-západ, Praha-sever, Praha-východ). In 1928, the name was changed to the District Office of Praha-venkov. It was headed by the district governor. The office was abolished in 1942, and its territory was divided into two new administrative units, Praha-venkov-jih and Praha-venkov-sever.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents arising from the activities of the district office. It contains official books, file material, accounting material and associated agenda. Documents concerning Jews can be found in the following categories: Presidium files - no. 1428/5 Settlement of Polish Jews, 1933; no. 1045 Anti-Jewish slogans on the railway bridge in Trnová, 1934; no. 120 The use of Jews in German intelligence, 1936; no. 1104 German emigrants of Jewish origin in Všenory, 1938; 1651 Anti-Jewish activities in Zbraslav, 1938; no. 282 Jewish members of the civil service, 1939; no. 450 Files concerning politically active Jewish emigrants, 1939; no. 826 Disciplinary proceedings with Ing. Václav Řepa for his slow compilation of a statement of Jewish agricultural and forest property, 1939; no. 921 Jewish enterprises and shops in the district of Praha-venkov, 1939; no. 1044 Eviction of Jews, 1939; no. 1295 Imposition of forced local residence on all Polish Jews from the age of 16, 1939; no. 1363/1939, no. 1324/1940 and no. 1993/1940 Anti-Jewish articles in the Vlajka journal, 1939; no. 349 Detecting Jewish cottages, 1940; no. 1346 Housing situation and behavior of Jews in Řevnice, 1940; no. 1503 Persecution of Jews in Roztoky, 1940; no. 1747 Marking of Jewish shops and factories, 1940; no. 165 Exclusion of Jews from fishing, 1941; no. 294 Prohibition of books authored by Jews and of the Scout Union, 1941; no. 562 Investigation of contacts of municipal employees in Libčice with the Jewish population, 1941. Restrictive measures against Jews concerning their visiting various places, and setting hours for Jews, can be found in the following files: no. 1045/1940; no. 319/1941; no. 830/1941; no. 881/1941; no. 1591/1941; no. 1551/1941; no. 853 Putting flags on the houses where Jewish families live (an inquiry), 1941; no. 1232 Jewish half-breeds and civil servants with wives or husbands who are Jews, 1941; no. 1479 Employment of Jews by Aryans and Aryan maids by Jews, 1941. Books and files: Religious conversions, inv. no. 92-97 (1931-1939); List of conscripts (year of birth 1908, 1909, 1012, 1914, 1915, 1916, 1917); Documents concerning Jewish registers (1925-1936), inv. no. 357; Documents concerning Jews from the years of 1938-1939, inv. no. 546; A large number of documents concerning Jews from 1940-1942, inv. no. 712; inv. no. 362 Various information about smaller Jewish communities in the vicinity of Prague, their cancellation, modification of districts and internal administration of municipalities from 1927-1936 inv. no. 737 Documents from 1940-1942 concerning Jewish enterprises. Relevant are also the following files: inv. no. 361 Representation of rural Jewry (1931-1934); inv. no. 361 Slaný, Kralupy nad Vltavou and Ješín (1933); inv. no. 367 Restrictions on Jewish Immigration (1930); inv. no. 367 Anti-Jewish slogans - slogans painted on railway pillars (1934); inv. no. 370 Třebotov - Jewish funeral fraternity (1933); inv. no. 483 Jews - members of craft and trade organizations (1939); inv. no. 483 Non-Aryan tradesmen (1939); inv. no. 503 Congress of Jewish Scouts in Aloisov (1937); inv. no. 511 Conversion from the Jewish religious community to the Catholic Church (1939); inv. no. 525 Jewish religious community of Zbraslav - election (1937); inv. no. 619 Forced Administration of Jewish Property (1939); inv. no. 660 Confiscation of Jews' radio sets (1937-1939); inv. no. 688 Confiscation of Jews' radio sets (1940); inv. no. 715 List of books and brochures of objectionable content (1940); inv. no. 736 Jews - restrictive ordinances (1941); inv. no. 760 Jewish religious community of Zbraslav - community management (1941); inv. no. 760 Evaluation of the Jewish Prayer House in Davle (1941); inv. no. 761 The number of Aryan and non-Aryand population, no. VII/34-13 (1940); no. 761 Luisa Austerlitzová - additional record of death (1940–1941); inv. no. 780 Jewish religious community in Prague - application for the granting of a medical-police permit for the establishment of a hospital for the lung patients in Jíloviště (1940); inv. no. 781 List of cemeteries and administration of these cemeteries (1940).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into official books (administration and registration), file material (registry finding aids and files), 3. accounting material, and 4. associated agenda.</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Šmilauerová E.: Okresní úřad Praha-venkov 1927-1942. Inventář, 1963, 124 s., ev. č. 65.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Quirenc J.: Okresní úřad Praha-venkov – Presidiální spisy 1929-1938. Catalogue, 1970, 166 s., ev. č. 81.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><subject>Polish Jews</subject><subject>anti-Semitism</subject><subject>German Jewish emigrants</subject><subject>Jewish emigrants</subject><subject>Jewish enterprises and shops</subject><subject>Religious conversions</subject><subject>Chevra Kadisha</subject><subject>Jewish Scouts</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
