<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>47</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Okresní úřad Praha-venkov-jih</titleproper>
            <subtitle>District Office of Praha-venkov-jih / NAD 47</subtitle>
            <author>This archival description was created by the Jewish Museum in Prague in the framework of the cooperation between EHRI and the Yerusha project.</author>
        </titlestmt>
        <publicationstmt>
            <publisher>State District Archive of Prague-West in Prague</publisher>
            <address>
                <addressline>Pražská 728, Dobřichovice, PSČ 252 29</addressline>
                <addressline> +420 257 710 492</addressline>
                <addressline>http://www.soapraha.cz/praha-zapad/</addressline>
                <addressline>soka-praha.zapad@soapraha.cz</addressline>
            </address>
        </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <creation>
        <date>1942/1945</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="collection">
        <did>
            <unitid>47</unitid>
            <unittitle>Okresní úřad Praha-venkov-jih</unittitle>
            <physdesc>
                <genreform>Textual material</genreform>
                 
                <physfacet type="condition">Good</physfacet>
                <extent>39,23 linear meters</extent>
            </physdesc>
            <repository>
                <corpname>State District Archive of Prague-West in Prague</corpname>
            </repository>
            <unitdate>1942/1945</unitdate>
            <langmaterial>
                <language langcode="ger">ger</language><language langcode="cze">cze</language>
            </langmaterial>
            <origination>
                <name>District Office of Praha-venkov; District Office of Praha-venkov-jih; The District National Committee of Praha-jih</name>
            </origination>
        </did>
        <odd>
            <p>District Office of Praha-venkov-jih / NAD 47</p>
        </odd>
        <custodhist>
            <p>The fonds was transferred to the Praha-jih District Archives in 1954, and in 1960 it was stored in the Praha-západ District Archives. The material was transported in good condition. It was arranged and in 1963 an inventory was prepared to it.</p>
        </custodhist>
        <bioghist>
            <p>The Praha-venkov-jih District Office began to operate in 1942 on the territory of the abolished Praha-venkov District Office (Zbraslav, Jílové and Říčany judicial districts). It was headed by a German governor, who was also the head of the Reichsauftragverwaltung. It was abolished in 1945 and replaced by a national committee, from which the districts of Jílové and Říčany were separated. During the Nazi occupation, three municipalities - Hostěradice, Hradištko and Pikovice - were forcibly displaced and a military training camp of the occupiers was established on their territory. In 1943, it was changed to the Hradištko concentration camp. About 500 political prisoners of various nationalities were imprisoned there, and many of them perished.</p>
        </bioghist>
        <scopecontent>
            <p>The fonds contains documents arisen from activities of the district office during the Nazi occupation. It contains official books, file material, and accounting material. The fonds contains documents about the persecution of Jews, the seizure of their property, the transport of Jews, etc. (sections I/1, III/16). Reports on sabotage acts of the Czech population against the Nazi occupiers and illegal organizations, arrests, executions, and persecution of the population (in the Registry Department III). There are also documents concerning Czech refugees from the border region after the 1938 Munich Agreement. Explicit references to Jews can also be found in the presidium files: no. 905 Prohibition of serving Jews by barbers, 1942; no. 1059 Opinion on Jews in Černošice and surroundings, 1942; no. 1428 Dismissal of Valerie Smilovská, an employee of the District Office, whose husband was a Jew, 1942; no. 1763 Compulsory report about Jews (Uhříněves) 1942, no. 365 Fire in the former Jewish villa in Říčany, 1943; no. 826 Josef Vilim, a tailor from Prague 5, having Mrs. Löbl's persian fur coat, she being of Jewish origin (denouncement), 1943. Books and files contain relevant documents: inv. no. 8 Conversions of religion, 1942; inv. no. 59 Jews in public service, no. I/1 (1942–1945); inv. no. 88 Population records, no. III/5 (1942–1945); inv. no. 95 Requests of Jews for permission to leave residence, sign. III/16h-1 (1943); inv. no. 95 List of transported Jews, no. III/16h-7 (1944); inv. no. 143 Jewish religious community of Uhříněves - duplicates of registers, correspondence, no. VII/25 (1943); inv. no. 165 Compensation for political persecution, no. VIII/18 (1945).</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <arrangement>
            <p>The fonds is divided into: I. Official books, II. File material (registry finding aids and files), III. Accounting material</p>
        </arrangement>
        <accessrestrict>
            <p>partly accessible</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <otherfindaid><p>Šmilauerová E.: Okresní úřad Praha-venkov-jih 1942-1945. Inventář, 1963, 31 s., ev. č. 64.</p></otherfindaid><otherfindaid><p>Quirenc J.: Okresní úřad Praha-venkov-jih – Presidiální spisy 1939-1945. Katalog, 1968, 125 s., ev. č. 76.</p></otherfindaid>
        
        
        
        
        <controlaccess><corpname>Jewish religious community of Uhříněves</corpname></controlaccess>
        <controlaccess><subject>Jewish persecution</subject><subject>Jewish property</subject><subject>transports of the Jews</subject><subject>Conversions</subject><subject>population records</subject></controlaccess>
    </archdesc>
</ead>    
