<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>33601</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Female, born 1931</titleproper>
        </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="fonds">
        <did>
            <unitid>Interviews</unitid>
            <unittitle>Interviews</unittitle>
        </did>
        <dsc>
            <c01 level="collection">
                <did>
                    <unitid>pustka</unitid>
                    <unitid>142</unitid>
                    <unittitle>Social Anthropology of filling the Void: Poland and Ukraine after World War II</unittitle>
                    <materialspec label="Web Source">
                        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://uma.lvivcenter.org/collections/142/interviews"/>
                    </materialspec>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p>The central concept of the research project is «social void», a phenomenon that was characteristic of Central and Eastern Europe during and immediately after World War II as a result of mass ethnic cleansing, political revolutions, forced displacement and migration. The project focuses both on the material dimension of post-war social change (e.g. acquisition of property) and the subjective sphere of social practices and relationships. His goal was to examine the processes of replacing the missing elements of social life with local communities of Poland and Ukraine. The interviews conducted as part of the project show how the void was filled after the social groups (e.g. landowners, wealthy peasants), representatives of ethnic communities (Jews, Poles, Ukrainians) and professional groups (e.g. shoemakers, pharmacists, doctors, or more broadly – craftsmen, intelligence) were evicted by the war and post-war changes. The analysis concerns changes in the ownership structure, economic dysfunction, transformations of social and cultural practices, as well as changes in relations and social norms. The conversations archived at the Center were recorded in a dozen of locations in Lviv, Ivano-Frankivsk and Ternopil regions by an interdisciplinary team of Polish-Ukrainian researchers. The research was carried out in small towns and villages, combining the methodology of microhistory and biographic interview as part of oral history. In total, almost 150 interviews were collected in Ukraine, of which 40 are currently available in UStories collection. The conversations recorded in Poland as part of this bilateral study are preserved in Warsaw at Archiwum Historii Mówionej. The project coordinator is Anna Wylegała, a researcher at the Institute of Philosophy and Sociology of the Polish Academy of Sciences. Project is financed by the National Humanities Development Program, registration number 12H 13 0584 82. Galyna Bodnar worked with the materials before their publication.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unitid>33601</unitid>
                        <unittitle>Female, born 1931</unittitle>
                        
                        <materialspec label="Web Source">
                            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://uma.lvivcenter.org/en/interviews/33601"/>
                        </materialspec>
                        
                        
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>An interview with a native and permanent resident of the village Barysh, now Buchach district of Ternopil oblast. The woman complains of her poor memory on many occasions, and some interview questions remained not answered. The conversation started with the detailed description of the history of the narrator’s family, whose mother, after becoming a widow, married an older local Pole, whose family was later evicted to Poland. The woman mentions that interethnic marriages were common for their village. She tells about the Polish lord (didych) of the village, his manor and household, the fate of the owner and his property. The woman tells in detail about the Jews of Barash: their places of residence, occupations, certain personal data, religious life, the attitude of the villagers, stereotypes. Not being a witness to the events, the woman only briefly retells the story of shootings of Jews in Buchach and Barysh. A separate conversation thread is the second arrival of the Soviet government, collectivization, religious life in the underground, eviction of Poles to Poland, post-war arrests and repressions. The woman witnessed a massacre of Poles by the Ukrainian nationalist underground in Barysh in February of 1945, which she vividly describes using the example of the killed family Ukrainians made part of. <br />
Recorded in Barysh. The interviewer – Marta Havryshko.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
