<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>30080</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Female, born 1930</titleproper>
        </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="fonds">
        <did>
            <unitid>Interviews</unitid>
            <unittitle>Interviews</unittitle>
        </did>
        <dsc>
            <c01 level="collection">
                <did>
                    <unitid>pustka</unitid>
                    <unitid>142</unitid>
                    <unittitle>Social Anthropology of filling the Void: Poland and Ukraine after World War II</unittitle>
                    <materialspec label="Web Source">
                        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://uma.lvivcenter.org/collections/142/interviews"/>
                    </materialspec>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p>The central concept of the research project is «social void», a phenomenon that was characteristic of Central and Eastern Europe during and immediately after World War II as a result of mass ethnic cleansing, political revolutions, forced displacement and migration. The project focuses both on the material dimension of post-war social change (e.g. acquisition of property) and the subjective sphere of social practices and relationships. His goal was to examine the processes of replacing the missing elements of social life with local communities of Poland and Ukraine. The interviews conducted as part of the project show how the void was filled after the social groups (e.g. landowners, wealthy peasants), representatives of ethnic communities (Jews, Poles, Ukrainians) and professional groups (e.g. shoemakers, pharmacists, doctors, or more broadly – craftsmen, intelligence) were evicted by the war and post-war changes. The analysis concerns changes in the ownership structure, economic dysfunction, transformations of social and cultural practices, as well as changes in relations and social norms. The conversations archived at the Center were recorded in a dozen of locations in Lviv, Ivano-Frankivsk and Ternopil regions by an interdisciplinary team of Polish-Ukrainian researchers. The research was carried out in small towns and villages, combining the methodology of microhistory and biographic interview as part of oral history. In total, almost 150 interviews were collected in Ukraine, of which 40 are currently available in UStories collection. The conversations recorded in Poland as part of this bilateral study are preserved in Warsaw at Archiwum Historii Mówionej. The project coordinator is Anna Wylegała, a researcher at the Institute of Philosophy and Sociology of the Polish Academy of Sciences. Project is financed by the National Humanities Development Program, registration number 12H 13 0584 82. Galyna Bodnar worked with the materials before their publication.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unitid>30080</unitid>
                        <unittitle>Female, born 1930</unittitle>
                        
                        <materialspec label="Web Source">
                            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://uma.lvivcenter.org/en/interviews/30080"/>
                        </materialspec>
                        
                        
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>An interview with a native resident of the village Tovste, Zalishchyky district of Ternopil oblast. The woman graduated from accounting courses in Chortkiv and worked as a statistician in a hospital. The interviewee’s daughter was present during the interview and often joined the conversation, expanding on what her mother was saying and adding comments of her own. The interviewee often complained of her now poor memory. She told the history of her family. The father returned from work in the United States and had a large household in the village centre with a house lightning and plumbing, which was a rare thing at the time. The discussion of the pre-war life contains mainly the description of education at school, the first teacher, and fragmentary memories of the interethnic cohabitation, religious holidays of the Polish and Ukrainian population. The Soviet period of 1939 to 1941 is retained in the memory as the period of repressions and eviction of citizens to Siberia. The narrator briefly recalls everyday life during the German occupation, eviction for work, shootings of the Jews on the local cemetery, eviction of local Poles, and distribution of their property among the Ukrainians resettled from Poland. A separate conversation thread is concerned with the personal life of the woman, members of her family repressed by the Soviet government, relatives from the Ukrainian diaspora in Canada who came to visit the village. <br />
Recorded in Tovste. The interviewer – Natalia Otrishchenko.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>
