<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
    <eadheader>
    <eadid>39225</eadid>
    <filedesc>
        <titlestmt>
            <titleproper>Female, born 1932</titleproper>
        </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
    <langusage>
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    </eadheader>
    <archdesc level="fonds">
        <did>
            <unitid>Interviews</unitid>
            <unittitle>Interviews</unittitle>
        </did>
        <dsc>
            <c01 level="collection">
                <did>
                    <unitid>pustka</unitid>
                    <unitid>142</unitid>
                    <unittitle>Social Anthropology of filling the Void: Poland and Ukraine after World War II</unittitle>
                    <materialspec label="Web Source">
                        <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://uma.lvivcenter.org/collections/142/interviews"/>
                    </materialspec>
                </did>
                <scopecontent>
                    <p>The central concept of the research project is «social void», a phenomenon that was characteristic of Central and Eastern Europe during and immediately after World War II as a result of mass ethnic cleansing, political revolutions, forced displacement and migration. The project focuses both on the material dimension of post-war social change (e.g. acquisition of property) and the subjective sphere of social practices and relationships. His goal was to examine the processes of replacing the missing elements of social life with local communities of Poland and Ukraine. The interviews conducted as part of the project show how the void was filled after the social groups (e.g. landowners, wealthy peasants), representatives of ethnic communities (Jews, Poles, Ukrainians) and professional groups (e.g. shoemakers, pharmacists, doctors, or more broadly – craftsmen, intelligence) were evicted by the war and post-war changes. The analysis concerns changes in the ownership structure, economic dysfunction, transformations of social and cultural practices, as well as changes in relations and social norms. The conversations archived at the Center were recorded in a dozen of locations in Lviv, Ivano-Frankivsk and Ternopil regions by an interdisciplinary team of Polish-Ukrainian researchers. The research was carried out in small towns and villages, combining the methodology of microhistory and biographic interview as part of oral history. In total, almost 150 interviews were collected in Ukraine, of which 40 are currently available in UStories collection. The conversations recorded in Poland as part of this bilateral study are preserved in Warsaw at Archiwum Historii Mówionej. The project coordinator is Anna Wylegała, a researcher at the Institute of Philosophy and Sociology of the Polish Academy of Sciences. Project is financed by the National Humanities Development Program, registration number 12H 13 0584 82. Galyna Bodnar worked with the materials before their publication.</p>
                </scopecontent>
                <c02 level="item">
                    <did>
                        <unitid>39225</unitid>
                        <unittitle>Female, born 1932</unittitle>
                        
                        <materialspec label="Web Source">
                            <extptr xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://uma.lvivcenter.org/en/interviews/39225"/>
                        </materialspec>
                        
                        
                    </did>
                    <scopecontent>
                        <p>An interview with a woman born in Lviv who is a permanent resident of the village Hlibiv, Husiatyn district of Ternopil oblast. The conversation started with the detailed description of the narrator’s family and childhood years. She faced the war in September 1939 in Lviv and shared her childhood memories of the event. Her parents were a hired labor force in the city. Considering the financial hardship, the family soon moved to the father’s home village, Hlibiv. After the brief account of the German occupation, the woman talked about the post-war hardship, family life, the unbearable taxation of the villagers, hard work on the collective farm, and the fear that was characteristic of life in the Stalin times. Responding to the questionnaire part of the interview, the woman told about her father-in-law who was in charge of the village during German occupation and his arrest and exile to Siberia after the war; the post-war life of the village. Retelling the stories of the locals, the woman shared information about the Polish landlord, his escape from the Red Army and looting of the manor. A separate conversation thread is the Holocaust in Hlibiv and its neighbourhoods. The woman recalls the starvation of 1946 and 1947 and people coming from behind Zbruch in search of food. Fragmentary were the accounts of the Ukrainians resettled from Poland, the eviction of Poles after the war, and fellow villagers who emigrated to Canada.      <br />
Recorded in Hlibiv. The interviewer – Wiktoria Kudela-Świątek.</p>
                    </scopecontent>
                </c02>
            </c01>
        </dsc>
    </archdesc>
</ead>